Yes.
So making you all see
the speaker not just
not part of the plan
but I'm glad to be here.
And my name is Vivek Natarajan.
And I am a research scientist
in the Health AI team at Google.
A little bit more about me.
Growing up in India,
my parents always
wanted me to be a doctor, to
be precise a medical doctor.
But unfortunately, I was
probably not good enough
to memorize all of
the biology textbooks
that you had to do
in case you wanted
to track the medical
entrance examinations.
So I ended up becoming a
computer scientist instead.
But as a great man
once said, "You
can connect the dots
looking forward.
You only join them
looking backwards."
So through a rather long
winded path, not too dissimilar
from how we actually
train our neural networks,
I ended up working
in medicine again,
this time armed with this
magical new tool of AI.
And I can tell you that my
parents are far more happy
with my life choices right now.
But they never truly satisfied.
But digressions aside,
my goal for this job
is to peel back the
curtains and give you
a flavor of all the
innovation that is happening
at the intersection
of AI and biomedicine,
and how that is being
catalyzed by transformers
and large language
models in particular.
So we will spend the
first few minutes
trying to work up from first
principles, why transformers
and large language
models are a particularly
good fit for biomedical data.
And then we will deep dive
into a few papers covering
a bunch of different biomedical
applications settings.
And finally, I'll
present my views
on how this field is
likely going to evolve
in the next few years.
And even though my voice or tone
may not exactly sound that way,
I am incredibly excited
by the possibilities of AI
in biomedicine.
And I think we have an
incredible opportunity
in front of us to advance human
health and human potential.
And my hope at the
end of this talk
is you all will feel the
same way as I do today
and perhaps join me.
So yeah, let's jump
straight in, why
transformers in biomedicine?
And sorry I'm going
to pick people
who are in person to answer.
So maybe if one of
you could volunteer.
Go for it.
Why not?
That's a good answer.
Sure, go for it.
We have a lot of [INAUDIBLE]
data, so [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah, sure.
Medical doctors are expensive.
And a lot of their job is
just like memorizing the DSM.
Yeah, that's an important
application setting.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, great one.
So I think all of you
were on the right track.
And so maybe if you just
look at different kinds
of biomedical data.
For example, what
are clinical notes?
I think it's sequence
of doctor gibberish.
OK, I did not say
that but let's just
call a sequence of doctor
speak or doctor notes.
Similarly, if you were to look
at electronic medical records,
what are they?
They're essentially a sequence
of a person's encounters
with the medical system.
What about proteins?
Going deeper into
the biological stack.
They are nothing but a sequence
of amino acids linked together
by peptide bonds.
And does anybody
know what this is?
Go for it.
I think that's how we
store medical records.
Sorry, again.
Well, looks like chromosomes.
It's like they [INAUDIBLE].
You're getting close.
Anyone else?
So this is in the Wellcome
Collection in London
and this is actually a printout
of the full human genome.
And note, they did
not cheat over here.
The font is super small.
And as you can see
there's a bunch of ADGCs.
The entire printout
contains I think
over 130 volumes in that shelf.
And each page is
printed on both sides
and it's a 4 point font
with precisely 43,000
characters per page.
So that is how big
the human reference
genome is, more than
billions of base pairs.
And so again, the genome
is nothing but a sequence
of nucleotide base pairs.
So what we are essentially
seeing over here
is sequences are everywhere
in biomedical data
and what is the
best neural network
architecture for modeling them?
And I guess since you
are all in this course,
I don't have to convince
you that the answer is
transformers.
OK, that's good.
But maybe I'll just offer
a few reasons over here.
Firstly as you can see, the data
itself is multimodal in nature.
And we just saw a few examples.
And as someone pointed
out, transformers
have proven remarkable
at gassing up
pretty much any kind of data.
And we are really seeing
this remarkable convergence
across fields, whether that's
speech, or LP, or vision,
or robotics.
I mean, pretty much everywhere
we are using transformers
and I think biomedicine
is no different.
I think secondly, transformers
are far more effective
at modeling complex, long range
interactions over sequences.
And this property
is particularly
important in the
biomedical domain
and we will cover this in
more detail later in the talk.
And finally, as
someone pointed out,
these data sets
can be quite big.
And you can easily get into the
billions of tokens territory.
And this is where transformers
with all the power
lies of operations and the
relative ease of training.
And maybe someone should
try training analysis
on these kind of data sets.
You'll realize that these
are much better suited
for the kind of
data sets that we
have in this domain over here.
So yeah, I think there are
a few more reasons as well
but I think these are the key
ones as to why transformers
are particularly well-suited for
biomedical data sets and does.
Any questions so far.
OK, great.
So now in the next
part of this talk,
we will dive deep into a few
papers applying transformers
to biomedical data.
We'll start with
clinical applications
first, and then go gradually
deeper into the biology
stack, looking at proteins and
genomic applications as well.
And what you will
observe is that
while transformers and large
language models by extension
are a great fit, often
you have to innovate,
not just on the modeling
side but also on the data
and evaluation side to
make these application
scenarios really work.
And so the first paper I
want to talk about over here
is this recent
work from our team
called "Large Language Models
Encode Clinical Knowledge."
The motivation for this work is
actually quite straightforward.
So if you look at medicine,
it is a human endeavor.
And language is at the heart
of it facilitating interactions
between people and those
who provide care for them.
Unfortunately, if you look at
a lot of medical AI systems
develop till date, these
are all narrow single tasks
single domain models lacking
interactive and expressive
capabilities.
And as a result,
what has happened
is there is this discordance
between what these models can
do and what is expected
of them by patients,
and care providers, and others.
And this in turn has
I think prevented
broad uptake of medical AI.
And you can see that, for
example you don't really
have AI in many
clinics out there
like helping us with diagnosis
And so on and so forth.
But the recent progress
with transformer
based large language models,
it offers us an opportunity
to change all of this and
redesign and rethink medical AI
systems with language at the
heart of it mediating human AI
interactions between doctors,
researchers, and patients.
And I will be honest
if I don't point out
that there has been a large
volume of work in this space,
particularly in
the last few years.
There have been various
attempts to train
language models in
the biomedical domain
with models of various
different sizes
on different core pieces
of biomedical data.
And while this is
exciting, the quality bar
for applications in the medical
domain is actually quite high.
And so what is
missing is actually
is that there is actually not
many good evaluation benchmarks
and evaluation protocols
and frameworks.
So we don't have the equivalent
of a big bench in medicine.
And hopefully, you guys have
covered big bench before.
And so big bench is
a benchmark where
you can assess large
language models
across a variety of tasks,
domains, and settings
but we don't have an equivalent
of that in the medical domain.
And further, if you look at the
evaluations that are typically
used in these previous
studies, they only
look at objective metrics like
accuracy or natural language
generation metrics
like blue or cider.
But these fail to capture the
nuances of real world use cases
in clinical settings.
So what we essentially need was
a good benchmark, and a task,
and also a good
evaluation framework
for evaluating these models.
And so to address
this unmet need
and assess the potential of
LLMs in medicine, in our team,
we decided to focus on the
medical question answering
task.
Why?
Because answering
medical questions
is actually quite challenging.
It requires reading
comprehension skills, ability
to accurately recall
medical knowledge,
and also manipulate
and reason about it.
And furthermore, the Q&A
task is generally enough
and can subsume a bunch of
different application settings
such as summarization
of clinical notes,
clinical decision
support, and also
primary care triaging of
patient concerns and so on.
So we've identified the task.
The next question
is, what data set?
And so when we look at
the literature over here,
what we saw is that there are
several data sets floating
around assessing model
capabilities in a bunch
of different settings.
So what we decided was we should
probably just unify all of them
and put together
in one benchmark.
And so we did that and
we called it MultiMedQA.
And so if you look
at it, this benchmark
now covers medical
question answering data
sets from a bunch of
different settings
such as professional medical
questions like the US
medical license exam
style questions.
It also includes medical
research questions,
those based on PubMed
abstracts and so on,
and also questions from live
users and consumers asking
about medical information.
And also, the setting changes.
It could be closed
domain or open domain
and the model may be
expected to produce
long form answer in one
setting and maybe a short form
answer in another setting.
And finally, we saw
that while the Q&A data
sets, which covered consumer
goods-- yeah, go for it.
I have a quick question.
How do you evaluate
long formats?
I'll come back to this.
OK.
So yeah, very quickly.
Finally, when we looked at--
Sorry, one more thing.
People on screen might not
get your questions in person
so can you repeat questions?
OK, cool.
So the question was how do we
evaluate long form answers?
And I'll come back
to the subject later.
And so very quickly,
when we looked
at the data sets that
actually provided consumer
medical questions, we found
them to be quite small in size.
So we decided to augment them.
And so we went out to Google
and looked at the most
frequently asked consumer
medical questions.
And so we curated a data set and
we added that to the benchmark.
And we call that health
search QA over here.
And so-- yeah, again.
How big is the
composite data set?
I'll come back with the
statistics, I'm sure.
So here are a few examples.
So if you look at the
consumer medical questions,
they are quite short in nature.
And so they come from the
health search QA and the life
QA data sets whereas I think
if you look at the USMLE style
questions, these are
like long vineyards.
And so doctors have to
really, really carefully
read through them and come up
with the right answer, which
often involves a
process of elimination.
So again very, very different
application settings
and so the model has to really,
really adapt and understand
it has to do well in all these
settings across the board.
And life QA is interesting
because the reference answers
over here were actually
provided by librarians
so that's another
good comparison
point for us going ahead.
And so in terms
of statistics, we
had a total of seven data
sets in this benchmark.
As I said, we cover professional
medicine, medical research,
and consumer medical questions.
They're again, of
various different sizes
and can be long form,
short form, open domain,
and close domain,
so very diverse.
And I think it provides a
very comprehensive evaluation
of models in this medical
co-sponsoring setting.
So if you have a task on the
benchmark, the next question,
again, I think I asked was, how
do we evaluate these models?
And as I mentioned
before, automated metrics
are actually deeply
unsatisfactory because they
fail to capture the
nuances of real world
clinical applications.
So what we did was
actually heavily inspired
by some of Stephen's
work over here,
was to put together a
human evaluation framework
for assessing these
long form answers.
And this had two parts.
The first part was
evaluation by clinicians
and we asked them to rate
the model responses along 12
axes pertaining to factuality
of the responses, ability
to recall medical knowledge,
do medical reasoning,
and also for the
potential of harm
and bias in these responses.
But if you look at the potential
end users of such medical Q&A
systems, these are likely going
to be non-expert lay users.
So it is also important to
get these answers evaluated
by them as well.
And so we also
additionally asked
a pool of lay users as to
how helpful and actionable
they thought the answers were.
And so that was our
evaluation framework.
And we also have the
benchmark fixed so now
we monitor the fun part of
building and aligning LLMs
to the medical domain task.
So in this work, we decided
to build on the PaLM
family of language models.
Has that been covered
in the course before?
OK, great.
But very quickly, I believe this
is still the largest publicly
announced densely activated
decoder-only large language
model, with the largest one
being 540 billion parameters
in total.
A few more details.
The model's trained
on 40 billion tokens,
25% of which is multilingual.
The data come from a bunch
of different sources,
including social media
conversations, web pages,
books, GitHub, and Wikipedia,
and so on and so forth.
And at the time of
release, the model
was state of the art on many
NLP reasoning benchmarks.
And also it was the
first model to exceed
the average human
performance on BIG-bench.
Further, over the last
year, PaLM-derived models
were shown to be super
useful in a bunch
of different
application settings,
including for code generation
which was the PaLM code
model, in robotics,
the PaLM second model,
and also for answering math
and science questions which
was the Minerva models.
And so we thought PaLM
was a very good foundation
model for us to build on and
use it in the medical domain
as well.
And overall, I think PaLM is
a true magic of engineering
but I will refer you all
back to [INAUDIBLE] paper
on this for more details.
I think it's a must read.
And again, in late
October last year,
Jason Wei and a few
others at Google Brain
came out with the FLAN PaLM
variant of the PaLM model
and this is basically the
instruction to and counterpart.
And this model was
even better than PaLM
and I believe there's
still the state
of the art on many benchmarks
such as MMLU, [INAUDIBLE],,
and I think it exceeds PaLM
performance by an average
of 9.4% across BIG-bench tasks.
So we decided to build
on the FLAN-PaLM model
and we applied a combination
of prompting strategies
including few short
prompting, chain
of thought reasoning, and also
self consistency to the 540
billion parameter variant.
And we evaluated it
on the MultiMedQA data
sets that had the short
form MCQ questions.
And we found that this
model was really good.
At the time of publication,
this model on the USMLE data set
exceeded the previous state
of the art by over 17%.
This is specifically
the short form value?
It's only for the
USMLE MedQA data set.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
OK.
And so you see that the
accuracy or the previous state
of the art at the
time of publication
went up by over 17%.
And I believe this was the first
LLM based AI system to obtain
a passing equivalent
score which was 60%
or above on this benchmark.
And similarly, when we
looked at other MCQA data
sets in the benchmark.
For example, MedMCQA
which is a data
set of Indian medical entrance
examination questions,
the model was again
the state of the art.
On PubMedQA which was
question answering based
on PubMed abstracts,
that was again,
the model was state of the art
at the time of publication.
And same story on
MMLU clinical topics
as well, which include genetics,
anatomy, professional medicine,
clinical knowledge, and a
bunch of other topics in there.
All this was great.
And then when we started looking
at the scaling plots what
we saw was that the
performance seemed
to be improving as we scaled
the model from 8 billion
to 62 billion to 540 billion.
And so what this
basically suggested
that these general purpose
large language models trained
on public internet seemed
to encode clinical knowledge
pretty well, and their
medical reasoning abilities
tend to scale with
model parameter size.
We also did another
experiment when we
looked at selective prediction.
And we used the self
consistency votes
to determine when to differ.
And this is important
in clinical settings
because doctors
communicate when they
don't know about something.
And if our AI systems
are going to be
used in clinical settings,
for example for diagnosis,
they should be able to tell you
when they don't know something.
And so what we observed here
was this fairly crude metric.
We were getting a linear
improvement in performance
as we change the
default threshold.
And this was quite nice
but in practice, this
is actually quite inefficient
because you are generating
multiple decoding samples to
be able to compute this metric
so we need a better method.
Just to be clear, what is the
current fraction [INAUDIBLE]
what fraction you
find the model asks?
Yeah, it's basically says
I'm uncertain or unknown.
And that's determined based
on the cell consistency works.
I see.
OK.
So [INAUDIBLE] to apply variance
and apply consistency samples.
Got it.
Exactly.
Oh.
Are models trained to be
capable of deferring itself
[INAUDIBLE] I don't know?
No because they're just trained
on this next word prediction
task and that depends
on the data set.
The PubMedQA has some
answers which are maybe
but again, we don't explicitly
fine tune the models over here.
So no, the models
are not trained.
Yeah.
So [INAUDIBLE].
No.
So this is primarily
based on the reference
in the data sets, which is-- so
this is all accuracy metrics.
So we already know between the
four options or five options
which one is the right one.
And so we just do
the classification.
Yeah.
So I'll come back to the
clinician evaluation a bit
later.
Sorry, maybe I missed something.
How do you measure
the uncertainty?
So if you know what self
consistency prompting, what
we do is we generate multiple
decodes from the same model
and then we see
the number of times
the highest ranking
answer is worded.
And based on that, you can
fix a threshold and say,
"If it's below this number,
I'm going to differ."
So if say the majority
answer comes up in your self
consistency decode only n
times out of k or whatever,
then if that n is
too small, then it's
very likely the
model's uncertain
so that's how we differ.
So you don't really see
a paper on the spot,
so it's natural that that's
where the rest of [INAUDIBLE]??
I think if you plot it
further, it'll flatline.
But again, that's not useful.
I mean, if you're saying
no to every question,
that's not useful
at all so you want
to have a reasonable definite
percentage over here.
Yeah, but 0.4 or 0.5 not that--
I think that's high.
I think that's still
high, 50% is quite high.
But again, this is a
very contrived setting.
But in real world
use case is probably
I think that number
should be much lower.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
I think balanced accuracy
might be a better metric
but we looked at some
of these data sets.
And one data set, the
skew was pretty bad,
the PubMedQA data set.
And I think no
one should use it.
So if anyone's reporting
numbers on that data set,
you should just distrust them.
And I'm talking about
very specific people.
But again, I think
as I mentioned,
these accuracy metrics are good
for publicity and pushing up
benchmark numbers and
so on and so forth.
But the real evaluation is human
evaluation of the long form
answers and that's what I'll
come to in the next part.
So far so good.
I mean, we were getting
results on these benchmarks
and we were very happy.
And so what we did was--
one thing you'll observe that
I have so far only reported
results on multiple choice
questions, short form answers.
So what was left for us to do
was to take these answers--
take these models and
generate long term answers
to the other data
sets that we had
and get them human evaluated.
And I think that is where
the real project began.
When we looked at the evals
by experts and laypeople,
it revealed very key
gaps and limitations
in the FLAN-PaLM responses.
We are often seeing
that these models
were hallucinating or
producing incomplete responses.
And when we asked experts
whether they preferred
clinician generated answers or
these model generated answers,
they almost always preferred
clinician generated answers.
So it was very clear that--
Sorry, I didn't
catch this earlier,
but [INAUDIBLE] evaluators.
Are these laypeople or these--
They're both.
OK.
And so what these
previous results
showed was while
these models already
encode some degree of
clinical knowledge,
to be really used in
actual real world settings,
you need to align
these models better
to the safety
critical requirements
of the medical domain.
But a big challenge
is we did not
have any kind of
supervised or feedback data
and so we really need
the alignment technique
to be data efficient.
But thankfully,
we had instruction
from tuning which was
introduced by Brian
Lester and a few others at
Google a couple of years back.
And how this method
works is it essentially
freezes the big LLM
model and only learns
an additional small
set of prompt vectors
which can then be
used to condition
the model that inference
when doing the generation.
And the nice thing
about this is it
allows very easy use of the
model across tasks and domains.
And you only need to carry
around these additional prompt
parameters.
And these tend to
be much smaller
than the billions of parameters
that you have in the LLM.
And the other good thing is
this is very computationally
efficient as well.
So if you were to do
enter in fine tuning,
often in our compute
infrastructure,
even with like a few
thousand examples,
that would take like a few days.
Whereas with instruction
from tuning, given
the data set size
has also reduced,
the number of examples that
you need is quite small.
And B, you're just updating
the prompt token vectors.
It meant that we were
able to get model
updates in like a few hours.
And so that was really fast and
enabled really quick iterations
for us.
So this was how we put together
the final Med-PaLM model.
We-- sorry, go ahead.
Sorry.
I'll let you finish.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK, cool.
So this was how we put together
the final Med-PaLM model.
So we used instructions
and exemplars
from a panel of
expert clinicians.
And these are in the order
of hundreds, not thousands
and tens of thousands and you
see a few examples over there.
There's an instruction,
followed by a model answer,
followed by an explanation.
And we use that to learn
the prompt practice.
And so the final Med-PaLM model
is basically all of FLAN-PaLM
plus these additional
prompt vector parameters
which are used to align the
model to the requirements
of the medical domain.
And why this works well is
because as we have seen before,
the model already has medical
knowledge encoded in it.
All we need is to
teach the model
how to use it properly in
the given application setting
and that's what these
parameters do for us.
So the question I wanted
to ask is, nowadays
you've probably seen a
lot about online chat.
And given the fact that you have
all of these human preferences
expressed by your
moderators, can
you guys explain how you guys
define a reward or preference
model and it was not
confined to [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah.
I think you can think about
different stages of model
development.
So this is pre-deployment and
release in the real world.
So you can't put a crappy model
out there in the real world.
So even before doing that,
if you can get like maybe 100
examples from whatever exploits
that you can get hold of
and use that to prompt you
in your model, that's better.
That's a much better
starting point
before you expose the
model to the real world
and collect preferences
from real users at scale.
And so I think RLHF is also much
less sample efficient compared
to the instruction
from tuning, again,
because you're probably trying
to update your entire model as
well.
So I think this is a
very good starting point.
And so they can both
be combined depending
on how depending on the
lifecycle of the model.
From your evaluations, are
your evaluations public?
The data set is public.
I'll talk about the
results in a bit.
Sorry.
I mean, human evaluations
contain publicly
within the data set.
You mean the model responses
and what the humans--
Human evaluations--
That's a good point.
So far not considering
releasing them but maybe we can.
OK.
Do you see a use case for that?
Well, just I was thinking
you had a bunch of data
in the preferences.
You frame the model to
express those preferences
and use that [INAUDIBLE].
So if I wanted to
train a word model,
that data is what I would need
to train that real world model.
Yeah, that's a good point.
I think the evaluation
data set is--
I'll talk about
this a bit later.
It's still small.
But I think if we scale it up,
and we are doing it right now,
I think we can
release that and that
will be I think a good resource
of what you're trying to do.
Cool.
So if you had the Med-PaLM
model as I said and now we
took the long form
answers from it
and compared that to
the FLAN-PaLM model
as well as to answers
generated by expert clinicians,
and as I said, we have two
parts to the human evaluation.
One is by expert conditions and
the other one is by lay users.
And so what do these
results look like?
On the 140-odd questions that
we got these evaluation results
on, what we observed typically
across the board was,
when we looked at
different axes,
while the FLAN-PaLM model would
be quite terrible honestly,
the Med-PaLM model would do
much better and typically close
the gap to expert clinicians.
So on this axis, you see
that the FLAN-PaLM model
has probably a 60% accuracy in
terms of scientific consensus.
The Med-PaLM palm model
improves and improves
on that quite a bit
and closes the gap
to clinicians over here.
Similar story on
other axes as well.
Over here you see
the clinicians rating
on the axes of how
well the model can
retrieve medical knowledge, how
well it can reason about it.
And again, we see the same
trend as in the previous slide.
Sorry to interrupt.
Yeah.
So the left call on the
left is correct [INAUDIBLE]..
So it's evidence of correct
comprehension and the right--
On the right-hand
side, it's incorrect,
so I think it needs
to be 1 minus.
No.
So both can be present
at the same time.
So you can have evidence of
correct comprehension, also
evidence of incorrect
comprehension.
Sometimes you--
[INAUDIBLE]
Exactly.
So that's why they're
not 1 minus so here.
I see.
But the trends are the same.
That's why I skipped it
but that's a good point.
Yeah.
So there's a typo over
here but this one pertains
to incorrect or missing content.
But this was an interesting
one because what--
when we were doing
this from tuning thing,
was we were teaching the
Med-PaLM model to produce
longer and more competencies.
And so you'd see a few
qualitative examples later.
But what ended up happening
the process was sometimes
the model was maybe producing
more incorrect information.
So that's why you see that
maybe in this particular axis,
the FLAN-PaLM model
was slightly better
but again, this was much
worse compared to clinicians.
Well, what does that
even mean [INAUDIBLE]??
It's a good question.
It is more like it's something
completely out of context.
So it may be irrelevant
to the question.
So that's where
I would say it's.
We also looked at possible and
extent and likelihood of harm.
And again, we see that with
the instruction from tuning,
we're able to close the gap to
expert clinicians over here.
Same on the bias axis as well.
Can you go back?
Sure.
How do you interpret
the top, exactly?
So I basically see a big gap
in the clinicians that 6%
[INAUDIBLE] how to clarify
exactly what that means?
Yeah.
So there might be certain
conditions or pathologies
or diagnosis like cancer.
And if for example, the
clinician has not caught that
or has maybe given a response
that does not appropriately
convey the severity
of the condition,
then that could potentially
lead to severe harm or death.
And so that's what we were
trying to capture with here.
So that's a very
high level overview.
This is I think a
very nuanced topic
and there's a framework for
it called the AHRQ framework.
And so we've linked that
in the paper as well.
And so I think that gives
you a very detailed notion
of harm and bias.
So I would defer to that.
But at a high level, this
is what I'm talking about.
Hope that helps.
All right.
So when later I read plus and
I say the [INAUDIBLE] possible
harm, which means--
what would I say?
Does that mean that
they recommend something
that could kill the patient?
Maybe they fail to
recommend something.
But they fail.
Yeah.
So it's basically a
misdiagnosis or maybe
failing to capture the
severity of a diagnosis.
This is typical in life
threatening conditions.
So it's more often
than not, not mistakes
but rather just
missing out on details.
Yes.
So I talked about bias as well.
And then, as I said, the
other axis of human evaluation
was with lay users.
And so we asked them how
well does the model address
the intent of the question?
And again, we saw
with instruction
from tuning Med-PaLM closing
the gap to clinicians.
And then we asked them how
helpful their responses were,
and what we see is that
while FLAN-PaLM responses are
considered to be helpful
like 60% of the time,
the number improved
to 80% for Med-PaLM
but it was still fairly lower
compared to clinicians at 90%.
So here are a few
qualitative examples.
And so what you see
is that physicians,
and this is typically because
they work in a time constrained
settings, their answers tend
to be precise and succinct.
But sometimes it's very hard
as lay users or patients
to decipher and
decode the answer
and get all the
full set of details.
And so what I think language
models like Med-PaLM
can help with is actually
converting the physician
speak to something that's more
easily digestible by lay users.
And so this is where I think
how these models will likely
fit in clinical settings
in the near-term.
Where they're going
to augment physicians
in terms of interacting with
patients and other physicians
and researchers as well.
Sorry, go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
That's right.
I think it's subjective.
And so that's why I think we're
still seeing lay users plan
performances to be helpful 80%.
Well, that's much
higher for physicians.
So it's not perfect
by any means but I
think this is where there is
a complementarity element we
feel over here.
And we've asked that.
When we ask people like, "How
easy is it to interpret doctor
notes or recommendations?"
And they often say,
"Oh, it's very hard.
I need to go back to Google.
Search for what
these terms mean,
what these abbreviations mean."
And so I think this is
where a language model can
come and take that note and
convert that into something
that's more easily digestible.
So I think that's the
opportunity over here, I feel.
So that was all on
our paper but I also
want to make very quickly
point out a very recent work,
which came out last week with
this rather provocative title,
"Do we still need to
make a language models?"
And by clinical
language models, they
meant smaller models
which are trained
in domain with clinical
data such as medical notes
and records and so
on and so forth.
And what this paper
basically suggests
is that smaller fine
tuned in domain LMs
are likely better than
general purpose LLMs.
In this paper, I think
they evaluated in GPT 3
with in context learning.
So I think that's a pretty
interesting and neat
observation.
I think there's a lot
of value for smaller
in-domains such as PubMed,
GPT, and a few other variants.
But I think one thing that
this paper does not do
is consider in
context learning--
sorry, prompt tuning.
And I think that's where some
of the benefits of this larger
general purpose LLMs shine.
And again, we haven't done
any in-domain LM pre-training
on these large general
purpose models.
But that's again,
an option for us
as well to do it on the links.
So you can take these
40 billion parameters
and then still turn it on
medical notes or whatever
domain specific data
that you can get hold of
and hopefully that'll
probably further improve
the performance.
So key takeaways so far.
What I wanted to convey
was general purpose LLMs.
It looks like they do
encode medical knowledge
and performance on
medical reasoning
does seem to improve with scale.
However, these
models I don't think
can be directly used out of
the box in clinical settings
and they need to be
aligned with the safety
critical requirements
of the medical domain.
And I think instruction
prompt tuning
is an extremely
efficient technique,
both on the data side and
also on the compute side.
And we should probably use
it more often depending on--
and hopefully the API starts
supporting it as well.
And these models appear
to be closing the gap
to expert clinicians, at least
on this medical questions
and answering tasks.
And while this is
hugely exciting
and has profound
implications, you
can all probably dream up
and imagine the application
scenarios over here.
I think comprehensive benchmarks
and evaluation frameworks
are necessary in order to
further assess and improve
these models for
real world use cases.
So I'll stop over here.
Any questions?
Why do you think the
medicine [INAUDIBLE]??
I think--
[INAUDIBLE]
A lot of it is because
these data sets
tend to get locked
in silos with privacy
and other kinds of
regulations which prevent them
from being put out
there in the real world.
So you have to have HIPAA
compliant systems for storage
and so on and so forth.
So it's very difficult to
get data out of these silos
and put together
an open benchmark.
So honestly, I feel
like that's probably not
going to improve the
skill of these data sets.
At least the open version
of these data sets
are going to remain quite
small compared to the big LLM
training data sets or the
computer vision data sets
on actual images and
so on and so forth.
But what may happen
in the future
is we may have more distributed
federated evaluation settings
where you take the model
into these private silos
and get them evaluated on
so they are never exposed
and put out there in the public.
But rather, we can have these
federated evaluation settings.
So I think that there's
some work on that already.
There's a system
called [INAUDIBLE],,
and we'll probably
see more of them.
Can you repeat the question?
[INAUDIBLE]
Sure.
So the question over here
was why medical data sets are
smaller compared to
natural image data
sets in computer vision
or LLM training data sets
and so on and so forth.
What do you think are
some of the earliest
applications of medical
LLMs deployed in industry?
I think the first
set of use cases
are probably going to
be not diagnostic in it.
Sorry.
The question was,
what do you think
are the use cases of medical
LLMs and medical industry
settings?
And so the answer is I think the
first set of use cases that we
are going to see are probably
going to be non diagnostic
in nature but more around, if a
patient comes in and interacts
with a doctor, can you
generate summary notes?
And can you do workflow tasks
such as generating letters
for insurance, for
medications, for reference,
and so on and so forth?
I think these stats are right
up the alley of large language
models.
And I think if not already, in
the next six months to a year
we'll see a lot of these
use cases coming up.
And I think that's going to make
doctors' life, care providers'
life much easier because
right now, they're
spending a lot of time
doing these things
and not actually providing care
and attending to the patient.
Diagnostic use cases I think
will take a lot more time.
We need a lot more evaluation.
The data sets, as we can
see, are probably not there.
The evaluation
frameworks are not there.
But I think in the
long run, and that
is the dream setting, right?
And then maybe a follow up.
I'm assuming Medcom
is not open source.
What do you think
the best open source
model is for medical data?
I think it depends on
the-- so the question
is, what is the best open
source model for medical data?
I think depends on the
evaluation setting.
So I think the PubMed GPT model
from the Stanford foundation
group is quite strong.
I think GPT 3 or 3.5
or whatever variant
if you can bring in some
domain specific medical data
and do some in-domain tuning,
I think that model can also
improve quite a bit.
So I think those two would be
my favorite starting points
over here.
So you're saying part
of the [INAUDIBLE]??
You can just think them
as vectors corresponding
to a few additional tokens.
So it's not really
human legible.
So the question was, what do the
soft prompt vectors look like
and are they human legible?
And the answer is
no, they're not.
Just a follow up.
You said [INAUDIBLE]
Do you really
believe that [INAUDIBLE]
on-site hardware, on-site made
by all of the teams that can
take these models [INAUDIBLE]??
Sure.
So the question was, given
a lot of the hospital
systems and providers
networks are quite low tech
and don't have good
enough hardware,
do you really think
federated learning
could be used for distributed
training of large scale LLMs?
I think we are increasingly
seeing a trend towards cloud.
And so a lot of these
hospital systems
are moving their
storage and data
and compute to standard
cloud providers
like AWS or Azure
or Google Cloud.
And so I think that helps
because these systems
on the backend side
do have the compute
to be able to train
these kind of models.
I think it's going to be
a very gradual process.
So systems that have high
quality infrastructure,
probably we're going to
start with that first
and then gradually work
our way into the long tail.
But it also feels like
something that will inevitably
exist in the world.
So 10 years down the line
or 15 years down the line
when we have these
distributed large scale
LLM training systems,
we'll always think back,
"Why did I even doubt
that this will not exist?"
It's so obvious.
It's something that has
to exist because that's
where all the patient data is,
all the interesting data is,
right?
So I think that
will just happen.
It's just not clear
whether that's
going to be done by one
company, whether that's
going to be done by a consortium
of academic or industry groups,
or whether governments
are going to be
involved or so on and so forth.
It's interesting.
You mentioned cloud computing.
It's actually-- you say
we're doing it better.
But we're still uploading
the data, probably
the same warehouse.
That's right.
So the question over here is
we're seeing cloud computing
but we are pretty much uploading
the data to the same warehouse.
The answer is true.
But again, I think
these are all going
to be separate buckets with
their own access controls
and so on and so forth.
So that is how you can
differentiate between them.
[INAUDIBLE]
It doesn't seem like that's
really present in the datasets
that we're [INAUDIBLE].
Sure.
So the question
was, has there been
any studies in Medcom looking
at private information
in these data sets?
And the short answer is no.
One of the criteria
for selecting
the data sets that
we used in the study
was to not include any kind of
personally identifiable data
or clinical data of that sort.
And that helped get
this paper out on time.
But I think that's
an important point.
It's unlikely that we're going
to have a lot of PHI data
in the public data sets
that we are training on.
But even when you're training
on say one private corpus
and then you're using it in
another application setting,
you want to ensure
that the model does not
leak out any kind of PHI
information during a situation.
So I think those sort of
studies are necessary.
We haven't got into them yet.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is,
what are the next steps
in terms of improving
these models further?
Yeah, retrieval is a
very important one.
Being able to cite
sources and especially
take in authoritative
sources and use that
in generating the answers
and also communicating that
to the users is very important.
I think how you communicate
uncertainty is very important.
So we've gotten to some extent
using instruction from tuning,
but I think that can
be much, much better.
So I think that's
another big bucket.
Again, I would stress
on the evaluation side
like looking at more data
sets, which for example may
do Q&A on health records or
other kinds of medical data.
I think that would be important.
And also extending
the evaluation
would in terms of scale,
having a diverse panel
of clinicians vote,
and also in terms
of the data that you're using.
Maybe adversarial
modifying the questions
to include demographic
confounders or something
like that.
I think those are all could
be interesting directions.
I think on the modeling side,
the interesting question
for me is again, this interplay
between smaller domain
specific LMs versus
larger purpose LLMs
and how that's
going to play out.
There seems to be some evidence
of emergence over here,
especially with
medical reasoning.
And so as you can
see, at lower scale,
sometimes the performance
is not good enough.
I mean, 50%, that's
a good number
but that's just not viable.
But when you get to 80%
or 90%, the products
really become useful.
And so we are seeing at bigger
parameter sizes of these models
but I don't know.
I think it's still an
open question we're here.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
The question was, is
hallucination an issue?
I think it still is but I
believe that you can control
that fairly well
with instruction
from tuning, any kind
of feedback data.
I think it's not
terribly difficult to do.
And so I think it might have
been overblown generally.
Especially when you are doing
it in a particular domain,
I think it's easier to control.
[INAUDIBLE]
What it looks like.
Say recently, there's been
reporting about [INAUDIBLE]..
I'm just curious because
this particular app,
do you think that's
very, very relevant?
And [INAUDIBLE] high
bar, the quality of it.
So I'm just curious
if you're even going
to speak out about [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
So the question was, there's
a lot of talk and noise
around hallucinations
and general purpose LLMs.
In this particular
application domain,
it seems particularly relevant.
And so can you expand on
that a little bit further?
Sure.
So what we are seeing is even
with an order of a few hundred
examples from expert
clinicians, teaching the model
how to communicate
medical information,
that is good enough
to get the model
to maybe stop hallucinating
or at least communicate
its uncertainty in a better way.
At least in this particular
domain or this setting,
it feels more tractable to us.
And the reason
I'm saying this is
we've looked at the
answers qualitatively
and we are seeing that
the model does not
tend to generate
super long answers
or make very
confident predictions.
But rather, the tone itself
becomes very reserved
and it starts using
terms like maybe
this needs to be done further
or something like that
which communicates uncertainty.
So how well is that
actually correlated
with the representation
underlying uncertainty
that we have, is still I
think an area of research.
But I think this is
already promising for us
that it feels controllable
in limited application
settings like medicine.
But if you have
a general purpose
LLM I'm trying to answer
pretty much everything
about the world, I think
that's a much harder problem.
Do you think that would be a
feature of the domain data set?
In medical situations, doctors
are more reserved perhaps
and don't have
absolute [INAUDIBLE]
or do you think it's more
that you just specialize?
It could be something
else entirely also,
I'm just curious what you think.
Yeah, so the question is, do you
think the way how the model is
performing in this domain is
that a feature of the data
sets in the medical
domain and typically based
on how doctors communicate?
And I think that's true.
And I think that's
something we need
to build on and use over here.
And I think that's
extremely helpful.
And hopefully this kind of
behavior is general enough
and can be transmitted
to the model
even when it's used in
non-medical settings
to be more reserved
when it's communicating,
hallucinate less, and
so on and so forth.
So I believe that that's one
of the opportunities over here,
to use these benchmarks
come up with methods
that reduce hallucination,
communicate uncertainty better.
And then use that as a
bidirectional learning
opportunity to improve the
general purpose LLM as well.
So if you have any
further questions,
I'll come back again
at the end of the talk
but I want to cover the rest
of the applications as well.
So the next domain I want
to talk about is proteins.
And the papers
from now I'm going
to zip through them a
little bit given time.
But the first one I want
to talk is this paper
from a few folks at Google
Research back in 2020,
called "Masked Language
Modeling for Proteins
via Linearly Scalable
Long-Context Transformers."
So the problem here
is that modeling long
range biological sequences
requires efficient transformer
architectures.
And so in this particular
paper, what they introduced
was this performance
architecture
which approximates the SOC max
attention kernel via low rank
decomposition.
And so this does not incorporate
any sparsity priors say
like other methods
like the Reformer
or there are many others.
And this is good because
sparsity priors may not
be appropriate for biological
data such as protein
which required global
interactions to be modeled.
And then the other thing is this
model, the performance scales
linearly rather than quadraticly
with the sequence length L.
And the number of
random features
that you need to approximate
this SOC max attention kernel
m, is completely independent
of the input sequence length.
So just to very
quickly visualize
the speed ups and the space
complexity improvements.
What you are having
with this loading
decomposition is instead of
having fat matrices in your SOC
max attention kernel, you
now have thinner matrices
which are determined by the
size of the random features.
And that basically reduces
your quadratic complexity
to something that is
more linear in nature
and also leads to
space improvements.
Yeah, there are more
theoretical analysis and details
in the paper, and I would
refer you all back to it.
But what we see in
terms of results
when doing protein
language modeling
is that the accuracy
of this model
is on par with
transformers while reducing
computational costs quite a bit.
And so what this suggests
is that the approximation
of the SOC max attention kernel
is a tight approximation.
So that is good.
And then when you compare
that with other methods
such as the Reformer
or [INAUDIBLE],,
the accuracy is much higher
at least on this task.
So it seems that compared to
other methods that approximate,
like try to build more
efficient transformers,
this one is much better
for biological sequence
data, at least in this setting.
And finally, if you
look at the attention
of the amino acid
similarity matrix,
you can see that the
performa model recognizes
highly similar amino acid
pairs such as D and E, and F
and Y over here so that suggests
that the model is learning
the right set of information
that we really want over here.
So that was a two-minute
overview of that paper.
But I want to talk
about another one which
also I think is really cool.
So this one is called
ProtNLM, again,
by a few other folks
at Google Research.
And what this does is model
based natural language protein
annotation.
And why this
problem is important
is because the
protein information
is in very high demand.
So over 50% of all
known proteins that
have been sequenced, we don't
actually know what they do.
So it's important that
we able to decipher that
to some degree at least.
And then the second thing is
we may want to, for example,
find protein sequences with
given functions and this is
particularly important
in the CRISPR domain.
And so if you can train
bidirectional models that
can do this, I think that
would be incredibly helpful.
And the reason I
say this, again,
is that the unique broad
database that has over--
that has I think millions of
researchers worldwide using it
today.
And so getting this information
populated in that database
would be incredibly useful and
accelerate a lot of research
in this space.
And so the European
Bioinformatics Institute,
they have curated this
pretext data about proteins.
And so basically, you can
use this protein record
to train these models.
And so what you
want to do is you
want to maybe learn to directly
map from amino acid sequences
to natural language
descriptions of them.
And this problem is not
too different from an image
captioning problem where instead
of having a sequence of pixels,
I don't know if sequence is
right but if you have pixels,
instead you have a
sequence of amino acids
and they can range a
number from 2 to 40k.
And then what you
want to generate out
is a description of the protein.
And in this paper,
the way they do
this is they train a T5 model
on protein sequence annotation
tasks.
So the tasks are set up in
a bunch of different ways.
And the supervised
data comes from a bunch
of different sources in the
protein record that they have.
And this model is
an encoded T5 model.
So it's a very cool application.
And the results are that out
of the 56 million proteins
in that UniProt database
that were previously
uncharacterized,
49 million of them
now have associated
textual descriptions.
So we now have a
handle on what they do.
And so that's really cool.
And then the other one I think
which is probably even more
interesting is now
you can run queries
like find me a smaller version
of this CRISPR Cas9 protein
so that it can target
certain tissues better
and now the model can
come back with sequences.
And so I think this is going
to be incredibly useful
and going to accelerate a lot
of research in this space.
Already there's a
lot of momentum.
I think these models are
going to further help.
So that was on proteins.
The last class of applications
that I want to cover
is on the genomics side.
Again, the first paper over
here was some work last year
from our genomics team
at Health AI at Google,
which is building gap
aware sequence transformers
for sequence collection.
So this module is
called DeepConsensus.
And so what role does this model
play and why does it matter?
So if you look at the sequencing
data lifecycle, what you do
is you go from
basically atoms to bits.
And so you have this
physical specimen that
hopefully has some DNA in it.
And you put it
through a sequencing
machine such as PacBio and that
comes out with the raw data.
And that raw data gets
mapped to a reference genome.
And then sometimes
there might be
DIFS between an individual
and the reference genome
and that can be corrected
through this model called deep
variant that was introduced
by our team a few years back
and that's open source.
And then once you
have this sequence,
you can then use it for a
bunch of different analysis
such as ancestry or just
basic biomedical research.
So where deep variant
fits in is it's
actually makes the raw
DNA reads that comes out
from the PacBio sequencer.
It tries to make
it more accurate.
And so how the PacBio
sequencer actually works
is it uses this clear consensus
sequencing algorithm where
the DNA molecule is
read several times,
and it produces multiple
different subreads.
And these subreads, they
do contain some errors
and so they are finally
assembled together.
And so what deep
variant tries to do
is it tries to improve on the
errors over here basically that
comes out from just this
circular consensus sequencing
algorithm.
And so how does this model work?
So as I said, the basic
task for deep consensus
is to use the CCS
data and the subreads
associated with them to
generate a corrected sequence.
And so in this example, when
we run through the model, what
we see is that while the CCS
identity was at like 95.7%,
the DeepConsensus prediction
identity was 100%.
So it's a fairly
simple task where
you're trying to
reduce errors that
come out from the PacBio
with the CCS algorithm.
And so the very natural question
is, where do these labels
come from?
So each CCS sequence
that you have, that is
aligned to a high
quality assembly.
And this high
quality assembly is
created by having many CCS
reads stitched together.
And so that ends up
having fewer errors.
And so you can then try to
use that high quality stitched
assembly and map that back to
the CCS trade for a given block
and use that as that label.
So that results in more
stronger ground truth
and you can use that to
train the model to improve
the accuracy further.
And so this is what the
model is trained on.
And so the model
looks like this.
It's a transformer architecture.
It takes these subreads
and this CCS read as well.
And it has a bunch of
additional context features
that come in from
the sequence itself,
the instrument sequencing
instrument as well.
And these are all fed into
the transformer model.
It produces a polished
segment and these segments
are then stitched together to
produce the final polish read
over here.
One thing I will
point out over here
is that in order to
train this model,
you can't use a
cross entropy loss.
And this is because
if you insert--
you often have insertions
in DNA sequences.
And so that can when you use a
cross entropy loss really throw
off the model.
Even like a single error
as you can see over here,
can propagate
throughout the sequence
and make it really worse.
So what you need
is a special kind
of alignment loss
based on distance
that can really capture this
error much, much better.
And so making this
alignment last work on TPUs
and making it
differentiable is I think
the real meat of this paper.
And so again, go
back to the paper
if you're interested
in that kind of topic.
I think that's really cool.
But at a very high level, how
well does this model work?
So if you look at the final
output, you have the read name.
You have the base
predictions and also
the predicted quality,
which can be thought
of as a confidence score.
And these base predictions
are often quite long
and so you can see that
continuous offscreen
because it's 10k to 20k
cases long over here.
And when you look
at the quality,
it improved quite a bit over
the [INAUDIBLE] CSS algorithm
over here.
The per read accuracy over
here improves quite a bit.
And so you may ask like,
what is the real world
impact of this kind of model?
So the answer is
this model is already
being used in the real world.
So at Stanford in
the genomics team
by Dr. Ashley and
a few others, there
was this recent ultra
rapid nanopore genome
sequencing paper where they set
a world record for the fastest
genome sequencing.
And this deep consensus
transform architecture
was used in that
assembly sequence.
And so in this
particular study, they
were able to very quickly
diagnose that Matthew over here
had a heart condition
due to genetic reasons.
And so they were very
quickly able to put
Matthew on the patient's
donors list over here.
So that's the kind
of real world impact
we can have with these
biomedical transfer models
and AI systems in general.
And very quickly, the last
paper that I want to talk
about is this paper from
DeepMind on Effective Gene
Expression Prediction from
Sequences By Integrating Long
Range Interactions."
This was published
in Nature Methods.
And the motivation for
this work is again,
that since the Human
Genome Project,
there have been thousands of
genome wide association study
hits where the goal is
to map genetic variants
to different kind of
disease phenotypes.
But a lot of this involves
experimentation and real world
experimentation patient
takes a lot of time.
So if you can do that with
machine learning models,
that's really great.
And so that's what they set
out to do in this paper.
And so if you look
at the gene itself,
there are 10% of
the gene are going
to be like coding variants
and these influence protein
function.
And then the way they
can cause diseases
is by disrupting the structure
of proteins that are generated
or by affecting the
protein-protein interactions.
The good part about
these coding variants
are they tend to be
closer to the gene
and so they're
easier to interpret.
On the other hand,
the 90% of the gene
is like non-coding variants.
And the way they work is they
influence protein expression.
So they are more like
regulatory sequences.
And so the way they
can lead to diseases
if they have any
variance is by disrupting
the transcription of proteins.
And given that these non-coding
variants can be very, very far
away from the gene and
the coding variants,
it's very difficult
to interpret them.
And so the question is,
can we try and transform
models that can
predict the influence
of these non-coding variants?
And so that is the
task over here.
And so this is a
visualization again.
So the paper again
looks at the--
it focuses on
transcription, which
is the first step in terms
of converting DNA into RNA.
And the way this is done is
you have RNA polymerase, which
gets recruited at the
beginning of the gene
by these proteins called
transcription factors.
And these transcription
factors have a binding site
which correspond to
these promoters which
are quite close to the gene.
But then you also
have these enhancers
which can be very, very far away
from these promoters in terms
of the linear space also
influencing this transcription.
And you may ask, how can such--
how can these enhancers
influence the activity over
here?
This is because while
they may be far away
in the linear space,
when the sequence folds
and in the 3D structure,
they will end up
being quite close to each other.
And so they can completely
affect the transcription
process over here.
So it's a very
high level overview
of what's happening over here
and in terms of the biology.
And so the question
is if there are
any variants in these
non-coding variants
and in these enhancers.
They may disrupt the
transcription factor binding
and this can in turn
lead to no proteins
and then finally
to diseases, right?
So we want to be
able to predict that
based on the DNA sequences
that have been generated.
So the problem is
quite straightforward.
It's a supervised
learning problem.
The setup is predict
experimental data
from these DNA sequences.
And this can take
many different forms.
The primary one is gene
expression over here
but then there are
also other tasks,
such as DNA accessibility,
histone modifications,
and transcription
factor binding,
and so on and so forth.
So as you can imagine,
the baseline model
for this task for many
years was the CNN model.
And as you start to get a
different set of layers,
you can increase
the receptive field
but there's a limit to that.
So in this work,
what they showed was
you can use transformers
instead and do
better modeling of these
long range interactions.
So the final model
is called "Enformer"
which is a combination of
this enhancer and transformer.
And so if you look
at the model itself,
it has a few CNN layers
at the beginning,
but then it has a bunch
of transformer blocks
that are stacked together.
And the input is
200kb DNA sequences
and there are
approximately 30 examples
that have been trained.
And the output is like genomic
tracks of this RNA expression
with.
And they have organism specific
so one for humans and one
for mouse.
And finally, one key detail is
that relative position encoding
that were used in this
model but actually very key.
And these relative position
encoding for modeling,
this power of interactions.
And as a result of using this
relative position encoding
with the transformer
block architecture,
they were now able to model
interactions over 100 base
pairs.
And so you see that in
the results over here.
So you have the
experimental data in green.
And you can see the
CNN baseline over here.
And you see that as
soon as you go far away,
you see that the CNN model
is no longer able to capture
these gene expressions.
But you can see that the
enhancer model is now
able to pick them up.
So you can see that as
the model goes far away,
the enhancer model is
able to capture this
whereas the standard model is
no longer able to capture this.
And finally, one very
interesting experiment
that they had in the
paper was they were also
able to predict
promoter-enhancer influences
and that prediction was actually
on par with experimental data.
So this suggests that using
this machine learning model,
we can sidestep a lot of
these wet lab experiments
and get key details which
could be super useful.
So yeah.
So very quickly, I'm sorry I
had to cram through proteins
and genomics
applications over here.
But I think what you
would see is that overall,
when you look at
clinical proteins
and genomic applications,
we see that transformers
have incredible
potential in biomedicine.
And with clinical
applications, I
think the challenges are
perhaps more centered
around data and evaluation.
But on the proteins
and genomics side,
I think there are some extremely
interesting opportunities
to innovate on the architecture.
And finally, as
I said, there are
incredible bidirectional
learning opportunities.
I think the problem
of modeling long range
interactions, that's
useful beyond proteins,
beyond genomics.
I think it's useful
in genomics and so I
think any architecture
improvement over here
can inspire wider
progress in AI.
So I think that's a big
reason to work on this.
Any questions so far?
Sorry, I covered a lot
of ground over here.
Apologies for that.
But I think these
are super cool papers
and you should go
back and read them.
So quite finally, I
want to maybe spend
a couple of minutes
touching on how
I see the future of
biomedical AI evolving.
Overall, I believe it's
not a question of if AI
will transform biomedicine.
I think it's rather a
question of when and how.
And I think the
very specific thesis
I have over here is, given
the nature of biomedical data
and how multimodal in nature,
and with all the progress
and transformers cells of
learning large language models,
I think we have an
incredibly powerful framework
to leverage all this
richness at scale
and truly build foundational
medical AI models.
So I think that is
incredibly exciting.
And so I'm not--
I think you've already been
over here for far too long
so I'm not going to you
to recognize these people.
But they are actually famous
physicians and scientists,
some of them in front
of Nobel prizes.
And so I think what I
want to say over here
is there's no reason
for a scientist
to be different
from a physician.
They can be combined
together and that's
what I also want to convey
with our AI systems as well.
We don't have to separate
clinical applications
and biological applications.
I think when we
combine them together,
we are going to discover
a lot of new insights
and I think that's going to
accelerate biomedical research
and internally to
new discoveries,
and which is going to be used
to eradicate diseases, advance
human health span, and generally
drive human potential forward.
So--
Question.
I don't actually know
who these three are.
Sure.
I think the rightmost one is
Alexander Fleming, and then
Jonas Salk, and
then Paul Ehrlich.
So Fleming is penicillin,
Salk is polio,
and Ehrlich was bunch
of different stuff.
And so maybe--
I lost this question to all
of you, which field of AI
do you think will--
which field do you think AI will
win the first Nobel Prize in?
You don't have to
answer, just think.
[CLASSROOM DISCUSSION]
Six.
[INAUDIBLE]
No, economics is
not a Nobel prize.
It is.
No, there's like
eight Nobel prizes.
Oh, OK.
But it's [INAUDIBLE].
[INAUDIBLE]
Because was like,
it's not a real field.
I'm not going to give
these people a prize.
I think economics
is another place.
[INAUDIBLE]
It is.
It's associated with
the Nobel Foundation.
No.
No?
OK.
I think it is.
The whole point of Nobel
was like, this is a joke.
I'm not awarding these people.
And then economists were
like, wait, wait, we're real.
And then they [INAUDIBLE]
economics Nobel Prize.
OK.
[INAUDIBLE] oh, he
invented this drug
that cured cancer or something.
That's right.
So I also feel the
same way, and I
hope the overwhelming
majority of you
also think that it's
going to be in medicine.
And I'm going to
end on that note.
Huge thank you to all my
collaborators and teammates
for most importantly
allowing me to steal slides.
And then also, thank
you to all of you
for patiently
listening over here.
Hopefully, this was helpful.